YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series V. Program Subjects
Sophia Smith Collection
In addition to the minutes and reports noted above in SERIES I of RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, Health secretaries reported to the City Department in early years, the Field Division, 1928-31; the National Services Division, 1932-39; and the Community Division in the 1940s. Their reports can be found in RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS in the Minutes and Reports in SERIES I. SERVICES TO ASSOCIATIONS. There are also files related to pool audits, and legal files related to pool accidents in the Community Associations files in SERIES IV.
Studies on YWCA gymnasiums and pool facilities can be found in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE in SERIES IV. DATA AND STATISTICS.
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK has many reports on health and recreation work in YWCAs in other countries.
There are many photographs of the health and sports programs in the community associations in RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
The YWCA made extensive use of Videotaped public service announcements and training materials for its ENCORE and Nike/YWCA Sports and Fitness Programs in the 1990s. These materials can be found in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIALS along with news coverage of these programs.
SUBSERIES C. MUSIC
Probably as a result of its religious origins, music, particularly participatory singing of hymns and folk songs from all over the world, was a part of Association meetings and events from very beginning. Music was seen as a contributing force to creative living and used as a means to foster international understanding and appreciation of other cultures. In its use of music, the Association highlighted participation rather than performance, and emphasized music as a valuable group participation opportunity that could provide fellowship, mood, content, and focus to events.
National music staff encouraged the effective use of music in programs at Community YWCAs and events such as Conventions and conferences through training song leaders and compiling and publishing song and hymn collections.
There was no formal music staff in the early years. Certain individual secretaries volunteered to lead the singing because of their interest and talent. These included Annie Kate Gilbert, Crystal Bird (later Fawcett), Sue Bailey (later Thurman), and Lucy Clark Street.
As part of the effort to counteract rampant xenophobia during World War I, staff in the War Work Council's Department for Work with Foreign-Born Women researched and compiled information on folk customs, costumes, folk lore, festivals, and music. One product of this effort was the two-volume Folk Songs of Many Peoples compiled by Florence Botsford and published by the YWCA in 1920 and 1921.
In 1925 Imogene Ireland, formerly an Industrial staff member, was "called" to direct music at Convention and conferences on a part-time basis under which she worked two-fifths time for the National Board and three-fifths for YWCA of the District of Columbia. Her position was directly subsidized by Katharine Blunt Parker, chair of YWCA's National Music Committee. Ireland edited The Song Book of the YWCA, published by the Womans Press in 1926.
Mrs. Parker had an interest in what the "right kind of music in the right kind of way" might do for the YWCA. She had been involved in the music program at the YWCA of the City of New York and later in Washington, D.C. with Imogene Ireland. Her husband, Judge Edwin B. Parker, left a bequest of $100,000 to the National Board to establish the Katharine Parker Music Foundation to fund a national department of music with a capable and experienced secretary in charge. The bequest came with two stipulations: Mrs. Parker was to be advisor "while she lives," and special attention should be given to stimulating and developing a love of music in Girl Reserves. The first national Music secretary, Marion Peabody, started work September 1930 as part of the Education and Research Division. Through the 1930s Marion Peabody urged Community Associations to form music committees to promote use of music in program, as a means to develop leadership and an effective group activity. She developed a music library in the national office and prepared lists and song sheets with "suitable and desirable songs for group singing."
Marie Oliver, music secretary in the 1940s, compiled the first edition of the YWCA's songbook, Sing Along the Way in 1943. The book "raised the level of songs" and included a wide variety of international folk songs, "better" camp songs, and songs of social significance, such as work and protest songs. Oliver put a great emphasis on finding and training staff and volunteers to lead music and created lots of training materials.
From the first edition, the "songs of social significance" included in Sing Along drew criticism from conservatives who questioned the inclusion of certain songs also included in the Communist Party songbook and any labor songs at all. The book included a wide variety of songs to "meet the concerns of different groups" and make it truly useful to the YWCA. One song in particular, "Joe Hill," was criticized again and again for its "incendiary" lyrics. Marie Oliver responded that the song "belongs to a part of labor history that cannot be wiped out simply by eliminating the song." Though she did not include all of the verses, she continued to put "Joe Hill" in editions of Sing Along as long as it was still used by the Clubs. The book was updated regularly until 1965.
As the National Association made more and more cuts to its program staff in the early 1950s, many of the associated "subject" committees, such as the National Music Committee, were also eliminated. Without energetic leadership from national, most local Committees were disbanded and the use of music as an educational tool in the Association quickly diminished.
Devaluation of the dollar in late 1940s meant that Foundation income could no longer support a full-time music secretary. Always eager to try new techniques, in 1950, the Association added responsibility for potential uses of newly available audiovisual "aids" to the duties of the Music Secretary.
After Marie Oliver resigned in 1952, the music position went unfilled for a number of years. When a part-time consultant was hired in 1959, she was put in charge of Music and Creative Arts. The program, which was much less ambitious, made much more use of recorded music. The Music and Creative Arts Consultant continued to produce program and training materials and put special emphasis on projects and training for Y-Teens and their leaders.
Participatory singing remained an important feature of Convention. Beginning in 1957, a small group of interested YWCA members who served as music consultants took over responsibility for Convention music. They also undertook various publishing and recording projects.
Anxious to find ways to increase teen participation in the YWCA and get them involved in creative experiences, the Association launched the Y-Teen Folksong Project at the Y-Teen Conference in 1965. The Project encouraged teenagers to express themselves in contemporary folksong style writing "songs about life as teenagers see it today." The best of the bunch were published in a special edition of the Y-Teen Bookshelf in the summer of 1966.
The position of Music-Creative Arts Consultant was one of many eliminated in the staff reorganization of 1970-72.
Administrative History
1930-32 Education and Research
1932-40 Laboratory Division
1940-44 Subject staff, Community Division
1945-49 Program Subject Department
1950-52 Music and Audio-Visual Aids, Training Services in Membership Services
1955-59 Consultant, Leadership Services
1960-69 Consultant, Creative Arts-Music in Research and Program Resources
Scope and Content
Music Program records include publications and related correspondence; reference files of general information and musical scores; historical research on music in the YWCA; general correspondence; minutes; planning materials and annotated programs from Conventions and Conferences; project files; and training materials.
Music Committee minutes and the selection of songs reveal much about the educational philosophy of the YWCA and the creative ways the various departments and programs found to contribute to the Association's purpose.
The Music Secretary's working files included in the Original Format Records provide an excellent sense of the aims of the work. They include annotated programs and preparation notes for Conventions, Conferences, and meetings with detailed information about what music was used when during the course of these events.
The reference files and publications attest to the Music Program's contribution to the National Association's efforts to foster intercultural appreciation. Reference and Project files (such as the Y-Teen Folksong Project), and forays into work with recorded music and "audio-visual aids" demonstrate continuing efforts to develop effective educational techniques and keep the program relevant.
Correspondence about the inclusion of "controversial" songs in Association songbooks in the Original Format Records provides insight into the challenges the Association faced during the Red Scare era.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The microfilmed records consist of just those materials submitted for inclusion in the Central File. There are Committee records, and the earlier correspondence about publication of YWCA song books. The inclusion of Music under "Arts" in the Subject Files reflects the addition of Creative Arts and audiovisual "aids" in the job description of the Music Secretary after World War II. Some of the Music Program publications are included on the microfilm, particularly those about the use of music in YWCA program. Song books and song sheets are less likely to have been microfilmed. The Original Format Records contain a much more comprehensive selection of music publications.
Music Program records are located on the Microfilm under:
Minutes and Report
Music Subcommittee [additional minutes were filmed with records in the Subject Files]
Subject Files
Arts-Music
Original Format Records, 1913-87, 5 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
While the original format records include most of the material on the microfilm, they also contain a large file of YWCA music publications and a substantial portion of the music reference file maintained by the Music Secretary. Mary B. Wheeler, Music Secretary, 1955-65, donated her working file, which included records she inherited from Marie Oliver, to the National Board Archives. This includes additional correspondence related to music, including such topics as the "controversial" songs used in YWCA songbooks, publication of songbooks (later years than those on the microfilm); and copyright issues; planning materials for music at Conventions, Conferences, and other events; project files; and training materials.
The Music Secretary's Reference files are arranged in two sections: General and Sheet Music/Scores. General is a wide-ranging subject file on topics such as various types and styles of music (from jazz, to Japanese, to rock and roll); music therapy; instrument making; recorded music; and music for children. The Reference files of Sheet Music/Scores are also wide-ranging and include Civil Rights Songs, Folk Songs (arranged by country), Girl Reserve songs, labor union songs, parodies, and sacred music.
The Publications include multiple editions of the YWCA's classic songbook Sing Along and the Girl Reserve Songbook. There is also a collection of YWCA songs, such as musical settings of the YWCA Purpose, "Follow the Gleam" (for many years the unofficial YWCA song), centennial songs written by members, and other similar items.
The Original Format Records are arranged in the following sections:
General and History
Committee and Staff
Conferences, Conventions, and other events
Projects
Training
Publications
Bibliographies
Program and Training Materials
Songbooks and Hymnals
YWCA Songs and Songsheets
Reference files
General
Sheet Music/Scores
Related Materials
In other Series in this Record Group
SERIES 4. CONSTITUENT GROUPS contains related efforts to compile and distribute information on international folk music and customs in Subseries B. Immigration and Foreign Communities
SERIES 6. PUBLICATIONS Minutes of the Publications Committee include discussions of music publications. Offerings related to music are listed in Publications catalogs.
In other Record Groups
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE contains additional material about copyright.
SUBSERIES D. PAGEANTRY AND DRAMA
Historical Note
According to The Use of Plays in Club Work, published by the Womans Press in 1930, "the most effective interpretation of life and ideas is by the dramatic method." Plays, skits, and pageants could be used to limber up gawky girls, teach them team work, improve their English, introduce them to literature, and to take pleasure in the simple things of life.
Formal responsibility for this aspect of YWCA Program began with the War Work Council's Bureau of Pageantry and Drama during World War I. The Bureau's secretary, Hazel MacKaye, traveled the country encouraging Community YWCAs, and particularly their Girl Reserve programs, to incorporate drama into their programs. Staff in the War Work Council's Department for Work with Foreign-Born Women collected information about folk festivals and pageants to add to the YWCA's growing catalog of scripts published and distributed by the Womans Press. After the war, the Publications Department included an editor of technical and dramatic publications until 1930.
Many of the scripts published by the Womans Press originated in Community Associations and their publication allowed a nationwide distribution.
As Womans Press activities declined with the financial troubles of the Great Depression and such things as World War II paper shortages, plays and skits were more-or-less eliminated from the catalog.
Though publication was curtailed, skits continued as a regular feature of meetings, conferences, and Conventions. Particularly popular were those written by Barbara Abel, who was Managing Editor of the Woman's Press, 1925-31, and later worked in publicity for the Chicago YWCA.
Scope and Content
The Pageantry and Drama materials primarily consist of scripts for plays, playlets, pageants, ceremonials, skits, "meditations," pantomimes, operettas, musical comedies, tableaux, water pageants, and festivals. There is a small amount of general historical material, lists of plays and pageants recommended or published by the YWCA, and some general reference materials, 1912-68, n.d.
The scripts' subjects are astounding in their variety. There are pieces on religious subjects, women's history, international and interracial relations, citizenship and democratic institutions, vocational guidance, blood plasma, child labor, consumer issues, industrial working conditions, health and safety, diet, unemployment, domestic service, American Indians, and many others. There are also skits and plays on administrative topics such as volunteer-staff relations, fund raising, and membership.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70
[see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
Scripts are scattered under Conference, Convention, and Miscellaneous in various places on the microfilm. There is some easily accessible information on the microfilm in the Subject File under World War I, Pageantry and Drama, and there are a few later scripts (1951-70) under Arts, Drama.
Original Format Records, 1911-84, n.d., 4.5 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
The overwhelming bulk of the Original Format Records is scripts. There is a small amount of General and Historical Material filed at the beginning of the Subseries. This is followed by general Scripts, arranged alphabetically by title, and then Christmas Scripts, also arranged alphabetically.
Related Materials
Scripts are scattered in Conference, Meeting, and Convention files throughout the records.
Elsewhere in this Record Group
The YWCA's general serial, the Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine (in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS) features many articles about use of drama in program.
In other Record Groups
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS includes reports by Pageantry and Drama secretaries Hazel MacKaye, and Sue Ann Wilson to the City, Town, and Rural Communities Departments.
In Personal Papers
The Sophia Smith Collection contains personal papers of Barbara Abel who wrote many plays and skits for the YWCA.
SUBSERIES E. RELIGION
Historical Note
As a religious group that sought to bring women together across lines of denomination, class, and place, the YWCA was a pioneering Christian organization. It was founded with a strongly evangelical Protestant emphasis and worked to fill in a breach of religious possibilities available to women in the emergent urban culture of the late nineteenth century. In its early, local incarnations it did so by providing instruction and a Christian-oriented space for women gathering in the cities who no longer had access to the traditional bonds of family and community. Student YWCAs marshaled the energy for religious service and expression that suffused college life in the late nineteenth-century. These groups also coordinated the efforts of service-oriented church women who wanted to escape the limits of church work within their denominations, which was often constrained by the vision of male clergy. In more recent years of the organization, religious matters have loomed in the background, becoming a shadow identity that uneasily accompanied the shift from the YWCA as a mainstay of ecumenical Protestantism into its contemporary incarnation as a women's social services organization.
From its inception in 1906, the national YWCA maintained the centrality of religious matters. It mediated and disseminated the spiritual emphasis that came out of the World YWCA, which delineated its basis as "Faith in God the Father as Creator and in Jesus Christ His only Son as Lord and Savior, and in the Holy Spirit as Revealer of truth and Source of power for life and service, according to the teaching of the Holy Scripture." (From YWCA of the USA Constitution, 1949). The national YWCA also coordinated and provided resources for religious work in local associations. In order to fulfill these functions, it devised its own religious programming and materials for uses both within and beyond the various YWCA constituencies.
Since religion was so central to the identity and programming of the YWCA, the subject is dispersed widely across the organization. The organization undertook religious work in concert with the variety of needs of its constituencies. It attended to the impact of spirituality on women workers, matters of race and nationality, and international fellowship as well as the spiritual life of students and of young women in cities and rural areas. In its early years, the national YWCA directly provided religious programming for these varied groups. It urged training in religious instruction on its employees, requiring religious and biblical studies at its National Training School and at conferences. Under the auspices of the Department of Method and its successors, secretaries and committees oversaw religious work taking place in community associations, and they developed a program of religious education through publications and workshops aimed at their diverse membership. Over time the groups connected to the National Board steered a transformation of the religious ethos of the YWCA from a Bible study-oriented, moralistic evangelism into an expansive, ecumenical space for discerning and living Christian ethics.
After the reorganization of the National Board in the 1920s and the diminution of programming in general in the 1930s, religious work became less centrally documented. It remained in the province of committee work through the 1940s, although unfortunately there are significant gaps in the dates of the materials from this work that remains. In these years, the administration deliberated regularly on the place of Christianity in the organization and the type of spiritual direction that would be most useful for the organization and for society at large. They continued to direct religious services at conferences and conventions and coordinate local religious programming, particularly through publications. Over the course of the 1930s and 1940s, the YWCA worked to foster cross-faith discussion and understanding, while acknowledging and occasionally indulging in programming that came out of its Protestant heritage and membership. Conferences and meetings, as large as the national convention and as small as routine staff gatherings, featured religious readings, worship services, and group prayer.
Although spirituality remained an object of much consideration at the administrative level, by the 1950s the YWCA grew less explicit in its expressions of Christianity. It continued with an ecumenical thrust, particularly welcoming Roman Catholics into its work, even as some priests and bishops forbade Catholic participation. Requests for religious programming diminished, and the organization's financial troubles forced it to curtail the publishing that had comprised a significant contribution of the organization to religion and spirituality.
The National Board approached the uncertain place of religion in the work of the YWCA at the mid-twentieth century in the 1964-67 Commission to Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement. This effort on the part of staff and volunteer committee sought to assess the significance of Christianity to the contemporary issues and programming. The study concluded that a dynamic Christianity, responsive to the increasing social consciousness of the young, remained central to the programming of the YWCA. Still, religion and Christianity waned in visibility. A consultant on religious matters remained on the national staff well into the 1980s, but the efforts of such work were overshadowed by strides made on questions of racial justice and women's issues more broadly. In these years, the national YWCA maintained a quiet attention to progressive Christian ethics as underlying its commitment to secular social programming, but the emphasis remained in the background.
Over the course of this history, various questions on matters of religion recurred for the national administration. The YWCA's relation to Protestant Christianity required clarification at numerous points. While the group drew from evangelical Protestantism and participated in the efforts of the Social Gospel, it responded enthusiastically to growing ecumenicalism and opened itself to a variety of spiritual outlooks. This caused an imbroglio at the 1930 National Convention, held in Detroit, when a faction successfully pushed for the end of the requirement of membership in an approved Protestant church as a condition of the full privileges of YWCA membership. Materials related to this controversy may be found among the convention material. Additionally, the YWCA occasionally found itself in trouble with Roman Catholic authorities over the participation of Catholic women in their programs, which increased significantly as the YWCA provided services to urban populations and industrial workers. Such flare-ups provided the occasion for revisiting and clarifying the nature of the YWCA's religiosity. These documents can be found in this series.